Register of the Paul LeRoy Jones papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul LeRoy Jones papers
1928-1994
80149
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 card file box, 1 oversize folder (5.5 linear feet)
The collection contains photographs, press releases, clippings, speeches, orders, maps, and a diary relating to Allied military activities in the China-Burma-India Theater in World War II and to General Joseph W. Stilwell.
Jones, Paul LeRoy, 1906-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
China Defense Supplies records, Hoover Institution Archives
Claire Lee Chennault papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Frank Dorn papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Henrietta Thompson processed volume, Hoover Institution Archives
Jack Silvey motion picture film, Hoover Institution Archives
Jesse Conn Miller photographs, Hoover Institution Archives
John N. Hart letters received, Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph Warren Stilwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
William E. R. Covell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1906 Born
1920s, circa Radio communicator in San Diego and San Francisco
1928 October - 1929 June Cadet, United States Air Corps
1929, circa Accepted a reserve commission in the Chemical Warfare Service of the United States Air Corps
1941 April Joined 7th Division, Infantry, United States Army
1941 August Assigned to Company D, 1st Battalion (heavy weapons company)
1942 February, circa Promoted to captain Worked as a railroad operations officer
1942 March Traveled to India and Burma Appointed liaison and courier to the Chinese 5th and 6th Armies
1942 May Participated in Joseph Stilwell's Burma walkout
1942 June Promoted to major
1942 October Appointed headquarters commandant and assistant to the acting assistant, G-4, acting as a transportation officer, possibly for Services of Supply (S.O.S.)
1943 October Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1943-1944, circa Public relations officer, China-Burma-India Theater Member of CBI Radio Team Oversaw delivery of supplies for Services of Supply (S.O.S.), China Defense Supplies
1944 Received Bronze Star
1944 December Returned to United States
1945 Worked for the Office of Information Services for Army Ground Forces, Public Relations
1945 September-October Public relations work in Okinawa, Japan
1945 November Returned to civilian life in California while remaining in the Army Reserves
Sources:
CBI Roundup, June 22, 1944, and November 9, 1944. Accessed through CBI Theater: http://cbi-theater-1.home.comcast.net/~cbi-theater-1/roundup/roundup062244.html
Jones, Paul L. "The Withdrawal from Burma and the Stilwell Walkout." Ex-CBI Roundup, May 1992. Accessed through CBI Theater: http://cbi-theater-3.home.comcast.net/~cbi-theater-3/stilwellpages/stilwell_walkout.html
Scope and Content of Collection
Consisting mainly of photographs, the Paul LeRoy Jones papers relate to Allied military activities in the China-Burma-India Theater in World War II, the Burma walkout in 1942, and General Joseph W. Stilwell.
The China-Burma-India Theater file includes the transcript of a diary that Jones kept from 1941 to 1945 documenting his experience in the China-Burma-India Theater and his interactions with General Stilwell.. The diary includes entries from May 1942, when Jones participated in the walkout through Burma to India led by General Stilwell. In the diary, Jones discusses his work with transportation of supplies, radio broadcasting programs, and his responses to world events. Explanatory notes, which Jones made at a later date, can be found throughout the diary. This file also includes documents by and about Stilwell, such as correspondence, clippings, press releases, statements by Stilwell, and the typescript "The Stilwell Story" by Finis Farr.
Jones held various jobs during the war that required him to travel extensively in the China-Burma-India Theater. Since he was assisting the Signal Corps, Jones was allowed to take photographs during his assignments. The Photographs contain images of areas where Jones was stationed, the construction of the Ledo Road, and Joseph Stilwell. Photographs that were previously separated still retain their original groupings in envelopes and have been integrated into the collection.
Additional photographs can be found in the Scrapbooks. The collection contains a scrapbook documenting the Burma walkout, which contains photographs, diary entries, and a map with a red line marking the walkout path. The second scrapbook documents Jones' time in Assam, where he was in charge of materials from China Defense Supplies that went over "The Hump." The third scrapbook concerns the surrender of Ryukyus Islands at Tenth Army Headquarters on Okinawa.
Stilwell, Joseph Warren, 1883-1946; United States. Army.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.
- China-Burma-India Theater File, 1928-1994
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes press releases, clippings, speeches, orders, maps, and transcript of Jones' diary. Arranged alphabetically by format.
  - Clippings
    - Claire Chennault's retirement, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - China, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - China and Japan, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Oversize magazine clippings, 1942-1944 (Box 5)
      Includes Life article by Clare Booth Luce
  - Diary of Paul L. Jones, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 1: 4-5)
    Typed transcript, includes notes
  - Maps, 1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Map of Burma, undated (Map case)
  - Orders, 1928-1945 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Subject file
    - Stilwell, Joseph, 1942-1994 (Box-folder 1: 8-11)
    - Wetzel, Nevin
      - General, 1941-1986, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
      - Engineer in the Far East: Memoirs of World War II in China, Burma and India, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 13)
        Includes letter
    - Miscellany, 1942, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
- Photographs, 1942-1945
  Includes black and white photographic prints, negatives, and slides. Arranged by format, with two groups of photographs. Includes photographs previously listed in the Hoover photograph card catalog. See also Scrapbooks.
  - Photographs previously separated, 1941-1946
    Originally listed in the Hoover photograph card catalog
    - Envelope A. 12 prints of military facilities in India, 1943; 18 prints of air base at Kweilin, China, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Envelope B. 61 prints of Kunming, China, including exercises with Chinese soldiers, 1944; 13 prints of Chungking, China, 1942-1943; 9 prints of funeral arrangements of Lin Shen, 1943; 4 prints of Chinese troops in Burma, 1944, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Envelope C and D. 97 prints relating to the construction of the Ledo Road, Burma, 1943-1944; 18 prints of facilities and troops in Burma, 1944 (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
    - Envelope E. 59 prints relating to the Battle of Myitkyina and the jungle training facility and general area after the battle, Burma, 1944 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Envelope F. 42 prints of Chinese soldiers at training facility in Rangarh, India, 1943; 9 prints of construction of an air base at Cheng Tu, China, 1944; 3 prints (unidentified) in the China-Burma-India Theater, circa 1942-1945 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Envelope G, H and I. 105 prints of Joseph Stilwell, William Bergin, Chiang Kai-shek, Chou En-lai, Chu Teh, Claire Chennault, John Dill, Patrick Hurley, Douglas MacArthur, Mao Tse-tung, Frank Merrill, Brehon Somervell, Daniel I. Sultan, and others, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 3: 3-5)
    - Envelope J. 15 prints of Joseph Stilwell with his family; 6 prints of Stilwell touring a Chrysler tank factory, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Envelope K. 16 negatives of the 73rd Evacuation Hospital in North Burma, 1944; 26 negatives of Joseph Stilwell, Claire Chennault, and others, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Photographs retained with collection, 1942-1945
    - Burma, 1944, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - [Cheng Tu Air Base], 1943 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Chinese military cemetery near Kunming, China, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Chinese troops near Ledo Road, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Chungking, China, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 4: 6-9)
      Includes headquarters
    - Chungking, China, and Washington, D.C., circa 1943, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Japanese surrender at Okinawa, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 11)
      Includes letter. See also Scrapbooks
    - Kunming, China, 1943, undated (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Kweilin Air Base, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Mandalay, Burma, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 14)
      Includes one print of area after bombing
    - Maymyo, Burma, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 15)
      Currently named Pyin U Lwin
    - Myitkyina air strip, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 16)
    - Stilwell, Joseph (includes "Uncle Joe's Chariot," Chungking and Kandy Ceylon), 1944, undated (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - War correspondents and photographers who went on first B-29 raid from Cheng Tu, China, 1944 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Slides, undated (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Negatives, 1942-1944, undated
    - Stilwell; Bill Bergin; CBI Headquarters in Chungking, undated (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Assam, India and Kunming, China, undated (Box 6)
      Roll of negatives
    - Bombing mission, 10th Air Force, undated (Box 6)
      See China-Burma-India Theater file, diary. Roll of negatives
    - China, Chungking. Chinese temples. Ledo Road. India general, 1942-1944 (Box 6)
      Roll of 35 mm negatives
    - Ledo Road, undated (Box 6)
    - P38 and [P51] planes at an air base in India, circa 1944 (Box 6)
    - Stilwell (Ledo) Road under construction, circa 1944 (Box 6)
      undated
- Scrapbooks, 1942-1991
  Includes three scrapbooks containing photographs, memoranda, reports, correspondence, maps, a badge, and clippings.
  - Burma walkout, 1942-1987
    - Original housing, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Photographs, 1942, undated (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
    - Transcript of diary entries, notes, maps, clippings, book excerpts, 1942-1987 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - Services of Supply, China Defense Supplies in Assam, 1942-1991, undated
    - Photographs, map, badge, original housing, 1942-1944, undated (Box 8)
      Housed in oversize box
    - Photographs, correspondence, and other documents, 1942-1944, undated (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Clipping on the Burma Road, 1991 (Map case)
  - U.S. Tenth Army and surrender of Ryukyus Islands at Tenth Army Headquarters on Okinawa, 1945, undated
    - Excerpts from letters to Winifred Stilwell, 1945 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - Photographs, 1945, undated (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
    - Okinawa Shima maps, undated (Map case)
- Declassified U.S. government records
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder by date of creation.
  - Records released in 2013, 1944 (Box-folder 9: 6-7)